<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator>
  
  
  <link href="https://worldview.themikejr.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="https://worldview.themikejr.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-03-02T09:39:35-05:00</updated>
  <id>https://worldview.themikejr.com//</id>

  
    <title type="html">Mike Brinker on Worldview</title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Musing, thinking, and wondering about theology, philosophy, and the Bible.</subtitle>
  

  
    <author>
        <name>Mike Brinker</name>
      
      
    </author>
  

  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">Bavinck’s Use of the Law</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://worldview.themikejr.com/bavinck-ethical-application/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bavinck's Use of the Law" />
      
      <published>2019-03-02T00:00:00-05:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
      <id>https://worldview.themikejr.com/bavinck-ethical-application</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://worldview.themikejr.com/bavinck-ethical-application/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But there is something else as well: the moral law that confronts us in the Decalogue, in the Sermon on the Mount, and further throughout the Old and New Testaments is not a case of “precept upon precept, line upon line, here a little, there a little” [Isa. 28:10, 13], but comprises universal norms, great principles that leave a lot of room for individual application and summon every believer to examine what in a given situation would be good for them be the good, acceptable, and perfect will of God (Rom. 12:2). Since the moral law is not a code of articles we merely have to look up in order, from moment to moment, to know exactly what we must do, there is in its domain a freedom that may not be curbed by human ordinances but must — precisely to safeguard the character of the moral life — be recognized and maintained. On the one hand that freedom includes the permissible, the adiaphora, and on the other what Rome calls the “counsels”. Error begins in both schools of thought when the adiaphora and the counsels are located outside or alongside of, below or above, the moral law and are therefore detached from the moral life. There is no right or reason for this either in the one or in the other case. There are cases in which what is in itself permissible becomes impermissible (Rom. 14:21, 23; 1 Cor. 8:13; 10:23); and there are also circumstances from which abstention from marriage (Matt. 19:11; 1 Cor. 7:7), giving up remuneration (1 Cor. 9:14- 19), the renunciation of all earthly goods (Matt. 19:21), or the like is a duty. But in “doing” these good works, one is not accomplishing anything that is outside of the moral law or surpasses it. For there is a difference between a law that furnishes universally valid rules and a duty that is inferred from the law in a given case for everyone personally. Those who lose sight of this and assume the existence of a series of good works that really lie outside of and surpass the moral law fail to honor its unity and universality and degrade it.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Herman Bavinck, Reformed Dogmatics Vol. 4, pp. 259 - 260&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Mike Brinker</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      
        <category term="Quotes" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">But there is something else as well: the moral law that confronts us in the Decalogue, in the Sermon on the Mount, and further throughout the Old and New Testaments is not a case of “precept upon precept, line upon line, here a little, there a little” [Isa. 28:10, 13], but comprises universal norms, great principles that leave a lot of room for individual application and summon every believer to examine what in a given situation would be good for them be the good, acceptable, and perfect will of God (Rom. 12:2). Since the moral law is not a code of articles we merely have to look up in order, from moment to moment, to know exactly what we must do, there is in its domain a freedom that may not be curbed by human ordinances but must — precisely to safeguard the character of the moral life — be recognized and maintained. On the one hand that freedom includes the permissible, the adiaphora, and on the other what Rome calls the “counsels”. Error begins in both schools of thought when the adiaphora and the counsels are located outside or alongside of, below or above, the moral law and are therefore detached from the moral life. There is no right or reason for this either in the one or in the other case. There are cases in which what is in itself permissible becomes impermissible (Rom. 14:21, 23; 1 Cor. 8:13; 10:23); and there are also circumstances from which abstention from marriage (Matt. 19:11; 1 Cor. 7:7), giving up remuneration (1 Cor. 9:14- 19), the renunciation of all earthly goods (Matt. 19:21), or the like is a duty. But in “doing” these good works, one is not accomplishing anything that is outside of the moral law or surpasses it. For there is a difference between a law that furnishes universally valid rules and a duty that is inferred from the law in a given case for everyone personally. Those who lose sight of this and assume the existence of a series of good works that really lie outside of and surpass the moral law fail to honor its unity and universality and degrade it. Herman Bavinck, Reformed Dogmatics Vol. 4, pp. 259 - 260</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
  
    <entry>
      
      <title type="html">3 Reasons Why ‘Literal’ Interpretation Should Be Abandoned</title>
      
      
      <link href="https://worldview.themikejr.com/3-reasons-to-abandon-literal-interpretation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="3 Reasons Why 'Literal' Interpretation Should Be Abandoned" />
      
      <published>2019-02-17T00:00:00-05:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
      <id>https://worldview.themikejr.com/3-reasons-to-abandon-literal-interpretation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://worldview.themikejr.com/3-reasons-to-abandon-literal-interpretation/">&lt;p&gt;As I have worked to understand the Bible on its own terms I have found the popular concern within Evangelicalism for the literal interpretation of a text to be contagious and unhealthy. &lt;em&gt;Literal interpretation&lt;/em&gt; is one of those ideas that most people think they know what it means when they hear it, but quickly falls apart upon further examination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to convey the issues that abound with the idea of literal interpretation I often start by asking a group of people that if I asked them to provide a literal interpretation of &lt;em&gt;The Great Gatsby&lt;/em&gt;, what would that mean? Would a literal interpretation claim nothing more than something like ‘the events in the Great Gatsby took place in space-time’? It becomes difficult to provide a meaningful answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another time I attempted to literally interpret a few lines from T.S. Eliot’s &lt;em&gt;Burnt Norton&lt;/em&gt; literally in front of a group. I ensure that my literal interpretation was unable to elucidate the deep, foundational concepts of consciousness and time that Eliot was probing at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is my contention that those who are serious about the Bible as the ‘Word of God’ should dispense with the term ‘literal’ regarding the how one interprets the scriptures.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What term should we replace it with? I’ll let you know when I find the right term (or perhaps someone already has). But for now, here are three reasons to never engage in literal interpretation again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-attempts-to-apply-the-term-consistently-abound-in-confusion&quot;&gt;1. Attempts to apply the term consistently abound in confusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first question that I try to ask of literal interpretation is “What precisely does it mean to interpret the Bible literally?”. Almost immediately one can get very confused when trying to define the term. When one begins to ask what is means to interpret various genres literally, confusion abounds. Let’s take the first few verses of Psalm 73 for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Truly God is good to Israel,
to those who are pure in heart.
But as for me, my feet had almost stumbled,
my steps had nearly slipped.
For I was envious of the arrogant
when I saw the prosperity of the wicked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does it mean to interpret a poetic phrase like ‘But as for me my feet had almost stumbled’ literally?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is the literal interpretation to assume that the author is talking about a time that he almost tumbled to the ground? If so, a literal interpretation of this passage is almost certainly wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is the literal interpretation to rightly take into account that the author is employing the metaphor of ‘walking’ used in the OT in terms if lifestyle and ethics? If so, using the term ‘literal’ when metaphoric imagery is being used is at best confusing and at worst self-contradicting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-what-most-mean-by-a-literal-interpretation-is-actually-quite-subjective&quot;&gt;2. What most mean by a ‘literal’ interpretation is actually quite subjective.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Chicago Statement on Biblical Hermeneutics&lt;/em&gt; (Article XV) states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We affirm the necessity of interpreting the Bible according to its literal, or normal, sense. The literal sense is the grammatical-historical sense, that is, the meaning which the writer expressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that the literal sense is the &lt;em&gt;normal&lt;/em&gt; sense which is also referred to as “the meaning which the writer expressed”. So in the case of the &lt;em&gt;Chicago Statement on Biblical Hermeneutics&lt;/em&gt;, the literal sense is the sense which the writer intended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most charitable way that a statement like this can be understood is that the authors of Chicago Statement were concerned about interpreters of the Bible importing meaning into a text over and against what an author intended. The problem with a statement such as this is that it is unnecessarily circular. The literal interpretation is the sense that the “writer intended”. In my mind, the goal of interpretation is foremost to understand what the writer intended! Most debates in interpretation of the Bible should indeed be about what the author intended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our current day, rare is the Biblical interpreter who claims to be assigning different meaning to a text than the author intended. If the best definition of literal interpretation is &lt;em&gt;authorial intent,&lt;/em&gt; then the literal interpretation is simply your own subjective definition of what the author intended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-layers-of-meaning&quot;&gt;3. Layers of meaning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we interpret a passage there are always layers of meaning involved. For example, in Revelation John received a vision. The first layer of meaning would be regarding the context in which John resided when he saw the vision and whether or not he actually did see it. The next layer would concern the meaning of the vision as described. I contend here that a literal interpretation of the first layer and a symbolic interpretation of the second is not problematic (and is indeed correct!). Only asking if we should interpret a passage like this is to ignore the &lt;em&gt;layers&lt;/em&gt;. To explain further I will start with a conversation I had with a friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was once discussing the anachronisms of literal interpretation with a friend who finds literal interpretation to be important as a hermeneutic. After giving examples of the problems that I see (summarized in the first two points) he offered the word ‘actual’ as an alternative to ‘literal’. It was important to him that I acknowledged the events being described in the Bible actually happened in the way it describes them. For him this was a very important component of literal interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this suggestion of an alternate by my friend his helpful in understanding his concern for a ‘literal’ interpretation, I don’t think that championing an interpretation of the ‘actual’ gets us as far as we need to go. Take for example part of John’s vision from the first chapter of Revelation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Then I turned to see the voice that was speaking to me, and on turning I saw seven golden lampstands, and in the midst of the lampstands one like a son of man, clothed with a long robe and with a golden sash around his chest. The hairs of his head were white, like white wool, like snow. His eyes were like a flame of fire, his feet were like burnished bronze, refined in a furnace, and his voice was like the roar of many waters. In his right hand he held seven stars, from his mouth came a sharp two-edged sword, and his face was like the sun shining in full strength.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my understanding, to champion an interpretation that acknowledges the “actuality” of this passage would only be for one to confess they believe John actually saw these things. The interesting work still remains where one must wade through the rich imagery provided by John and try understand what is being expressed by it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will probably ruffle the feathers of conservatives to say this, but when one is engaging in interpretation of this passage to determine what is being expressed in the imagery, the question of whether or not John actually saw these things fades into the background. Obviously if one has reason to believe that John didn’t see these visions but persisted in recording them and distributing them there will be larger, more troubling questions on their way, but please see that the question of actuality (which may be at the heart of the concerns of those who champion a literal interpretation) does not really get you anywhere in terms of understanding what single pericope &lt;em&gt;means&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are often layers of meaning on Biblical interpretation, some of which are ‘literal’ or &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt;. To ask if one is interpreting something literally assumes there is a single level of meaning or that all levels of meaning must be interpreted in the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, talking of a ‘literal’ interpretation is confusing and often misses the heart of the interpretive questions that really do need to be asked. Do you agree? Do you have a term that could legitimately replace &lt;em&gt;literal?&lt;/em&gt; Please let me know in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      
        <author>
            <name>Mike Brinker</name>
          
          
        </author>
      

      
        <category term="Scripture" />
      

      

      
        <summary type="html">As I have worked to understand the Bible on its own terms I have found the popular concern within Evangelicalism for the literal interpretation of a text to be contagious and unhealthy. Literal interpretation is one of those ideas that most people think they know what it means when they hear it, but quickly falls apart upon further examination.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
  
</feed>
